Mamie Himmelwright McIlwee Papers 161
People's Archive, MLK Library
Mamie Himmelwright McIlwee Papers
1932-1952
People's Archive, MLK Library
McIlwee, Mamie H.
161
3 Linear feet
2 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Correspondence Sub-series 1: Beautification of School Grounds and Petworth Library Sub-series 2: Civic Action Series 2: Legal Documents Series 3: Memoranda Series 4: Photographs Series 5: Newspaper Clippings Series 6: Scrapbook
Biographical / Historical
Mamie Himmelwright McIlwee was born on August 8, 1886 in Star Tannery, Frederick County, Virginia to parents John and Hattie Himelright. Mamie married Branson Gilbert McIlwee and together they raised four children in the District, Mae, Hettie, Jay, and John. Mrs. McIlwee worked to secure funding for expanded classrooms, additional courses, educational materials, and grounds beautification at Roosevelt High School by serving on the Roosevelt Parent Teacher Association as a member of the Legislative Committee and Chairman of the Committee on Beautifying School and Library Grounds. Additionally Mrs. McIlwee was a member of the Petworth and Manor Park Citizens Associations. Mrs. McIlwee passed August 3, 1967 at the National Lutheran Home for the Aged in Northeast D.C.
Custodial History
The provenance is unknown. No Deed of Gift was identified for this collecton.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes correspondence, legal documents, photographs, and newspaper clippings pertaining to Mamie H. McIlwee's work advocating for resources for Petworth public schools and libraries.
Public schools; Women; Libraries; Education; Neighborhoods; Petworth, Washington, D.C.; McIlwee, E,
- Series 1: Correspondence
  - Sub-series 1: Beautification of School Grounds and Petworth Library
    - Campaigns and Proposals, 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Campaigns and Proposals, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Campaigns and Proposals, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Campaigns and Proposals, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sub-series 2: Civic Action
    - Department of Health and Physical Education, "Posture Education", 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Protesting Petworth Liquor Licenses, 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Requesting Funds from Board of Commissioners, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Roosevelt High, Petworth Library, Petworth Women's Club, 1931-1936 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters Against the "Dog Interest", 1938-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1934-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series 2: Legal Documents
  - Legal Documents, District of Columbia Appropriation Bill Excerpts, 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series 3: Memoranda
  - The Beautification of School Grounds, 1933-1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Roosevelt High, Coolidge High, 1934-1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Petworth Public Library and Neighborhood History, 1917-1951 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series 4: Photographs
  - Unidentified buildings, 1932-1970 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series 5: Newspaper Clippings
  - Newspaper Clippings - Washington Post and Evening Star, 1933-1945 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper Clippings - Petworth Citizen, 1916-1930 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Photocopied Clippings - Washington Times, Evening Star and Post, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Photocopied Clippings - Washington Times, Evening Star and Post, 1939-1952 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series 6: Scrapbook
  - Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings, 1936-1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)